Finding Aid for James B. Angell Papers
Bentley Historical Library
James B. Angell Papers
1845-1916
Bentley Historical Library
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916
851644 Aa 2 Ac
16.5 linear feet (in 17 boxes)
1 oversize folder
6 volumes
Papers of James Burrill Angell, the third President of the University of Michigan (1871-1909) and U.S. Minister to China (1871-1909) and Turkey (1897-1898). Includes correspondence, lectures and lecture notes, addresses and articles, subject files and personal materials, and photographs.
The bulk of the collection was transferred from the William Clements Library, (donor no. 716 ) in 1939. Additional materials came from Robert C. Angell, (donor no. 485 ) and Lois Angell McLaughlin, (donor no. 237 )
The collection is open for research.
James B. Angell was a college president and diplomat. Born in Scituate, Rhode Island on January 7, 1829, Angell was a graduate of Brown University, class of 1849. After a period of travel and study, he joined the faculty of Brown soon after receiving his A.M. in 1853 as professor of modern languages. Angell married Sarah Caswell in 1855, daughter of Brown faculty and future president, Alexis Caswell. He resigned in 1860 to assume the editorship of the Providence Journal, a newspaper he had been writing for since 1858. As editor, Angell was especially interested in topics relating to international law and politics.
In 1866, Angell resigned to accept the presidency of the University of Vermont. In 1869, he was offered the presidency of the University of Michigan. After initially refusing the offer, Angell, after more than a year of negotiation with the regents, accepted the offer to come to Ann Arbor on February 7, 1871. He would remain as president until his retirement in 1909.
Because of his expertise in international affairs, Angell was called upon for occasional diplomatic service. He was minister to China from 1880 to 1881 and a member of a commission of three to negotiate a new immigration treaty which limited but did not absolutely prohibit the entry and residence of Chinese laborers into the United States. Angell remained in China until October 1881 and resumed his academic duties in February 1882.
In 1887, President Grover Cleveland selected Angell to serve on the Anglo-American International Commission on Canadian Fisheries. Later in Cleveland's second administration, Angell was named chairman of the Canadian-American Commission on Deep Waterways from Lakes to Sea. Angell's last diplomatic venture was as U.S. Minister to Turkey, serving from 1897 to 1898.
Angell died April 1, 1916.
The James B. Angell collection has been organized into five series of papers:
Correspondence -- Boxes 1-7 and 16-17 (index to correspondence)
Lectures and Lecture Notes -- Box 7
Addresses and Articles -- Boxes 7-10
Subject Files and Personal Papers -- Boxes 10-13
Photographs -- Boxes 14-15
The Angell papers documents Angell's academic and diplomatic career. There is extensive material on all phases of University of Michigan business, particularly Angell's contacts with the state legislature, the board of regents, faculty relations, and the various schools, colleges, departments and divisions. Much of the correspondence and the Angell diaries relate to his diplomatic missions, higher education in the United States, and family matters.
Ann Arbor (Mich.); China -- History -- 1861-1912.; Turkey.; Waterman Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Funeral rites and ceremonies.; Interiors -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Offices -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Women -- Organizations.; Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Prints.; Women's resources -- limited extent.; Digital file formats.; American Academy in Rome.; American Historical Association.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904: Saint Louis, Mo.); University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan -- Sports.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Medical School.; University of Michigan. University Museum.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. Semicentennial Celebration.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1871-1880.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1881-1890.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1891-1900.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1901-1910.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Angell, Sarah Caswell, 1831-1903.; Angell family.; Browning Club (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; President's House (University of Michigan); United States Fish Commission -- 1888.; University of Michigan. President.; Abel, John Jacob, 1857-1938.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910.; Angell, Alexis C. (Alexis Caswell), 1857-1932.; Angell, Avery Aldrich, 1807-1894.; Angell, Sarah Caswell, 1831-1903.; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1829-1886.; Bagley, John Judson, 1832-1881.; Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Beal, William James, 1833-1924.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.; Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Davis, R. C. (Raymond Cazallis), 1836-; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.; Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.; Duffield, George, 1794-1868.; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926.; Fairlie, John A. (John Archibald), 1872-1947.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Field, David Dudley, 1805-1894.; Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Gilchrist, James Grant, 1842-1906.; Grosvenor, Ebenezer Oliver, 1820-1910.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Harrington, Mark Walrod, 1848-1926.; Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, 1822-1893.; Hill, Arthur, 1847-1909.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Jerome, David Howell, 1829-1896.; Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858-; Kiefer, Hermann, 1825-1911.; Kirchner, Otto, 1846-1920.; Knappen, Loyal Edwin, 1854-1930.; Low, Seth, 1850-1916.; Luce, Cyrus Gray, 1824-1905.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Morrill, Justin Smith, 1810-1898.; Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.; Olney, Richard, 1835-1917.; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Sawyer, Andrew Jackson, 1834-; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Spaulding, c Mr. (Oliver Lyman), 1833-1922.; Stearns, Frederick, 1831-1907.; Steere, Joseph Beal, 1842-1940.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; University of Vermont.; Van Zile, Philip T. (Philip Taylor), 1843-1917.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Wead, Charles Kasson, 1848-1925.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
- Lectures and lecture notes, 1866-1879; 0.3 linear feet
  The series Lectures and Lecture Notes consists of text and notes for a series of lectures on international affairs, international law and European history which Angell prepared between 1866 and 1879.
  - Lecture concerning International Law, 1879 (Box 7)
    (268)
  - Lecture concerning Treaty of Nimeguen, 1879 (Box 7)
    (269)
  - Lecture concerning Treaty of Westphalia, 1879 (Box 7)
    (270)
  - Lecture concerning Thirty Years War, 1879 (Box 7)
    (271)
  - Lecture concerning from Treaty of Ryswick through Treaty of Utrecht, 1879 (Box 7)
    (272)
  - Lecture concerning foreign ministers, 1879 (Box 7)
    (273)
  - Lecture concerning Peace of the Pyrenees (1659), 1879 (Box 7)
    (274)
  - Lecture Notes, 1866-1871 (Box 7)
    (275)
  - Lecture Notes concerning international law, 1872 (Box 7)
    (276)
  - Lecture Notes concerning history, 1872; 4 folders (Box 7)
    (277-280)
  - Lecture Notes concerning 18th Century European History, 1872 (Box 7)
    (281)
- Correspondence, 1851-1916; 8.7 linear feet
  The Correspondence series is the largest portion of the collection and dates from 1851 to 1916. The series pertains to all phases of Angell's career, university, diplomatic, and personal. Angell corresponded with a wide range of educators, diplomats, and politicians. Two folders of note, titled "Miscellaneous" and "Regarding death of Sarah Angell" contain letters to James from local organizations and university departments offering their condolences for the passing of his wife. These folders also contain a number of obituaries from Michigan and Rhode Island newspapers describing some of Sarah's Angell's major accomplishments.
  The series also contains a card index to most of Angell's correspondence (Boxes 16-17). Appended to this finding aid is a selective name inventory to these correspondents listing dates of letters. The library also has an extensive (six volume), though incomplete, calendar to the Angell Correspondence series. This calendar consists of fairly detailed summarizations of the individual letters in the collection. The researcher should also note that the correspondence is primarily incoming only with very few copies of Angell's responses.
  The Asia Library of the University of Michigan has obtained microfilm copies of Angell's correspondence written while serving in China. The originals of the microfilm are located in the National Archives in Washington D.C.
  - Correspondence calendars
    - University Section, 1869-1888 (Volume 1)
    - University Section, 1889-1891 (Volume 2)
    - University Section, 1892-1895 (Volume 3)
    - University Section, 1896-1899 (Volume 4)
    - Various commissions and diplomatic missions, 1866-1898 (Volume 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1842-1899 (Volume 6)
  - Index to correspondence, A-S (Box 16)
  - Index to correspondence, T-Z (Box 17)
  - 1851-1859 (Box 1)
    (1)
  - 1860 (Box 1)
    (2)
  - 1866-1867 (Box 1)
    (3)
  - January-June 1868 (Box 1)
    (4)
  - July-December 1868 (Box 1)
    (5)
  - January-June 1869 (Box 1)
    (6)
  - July-September 1869 (Box 1)
    (7)
  - October-December 1869 (Box 1)
    (8)
  - 1870 (Box 1)
    (9)
  - January-June 1871 (Box 1)
    (10)
  - July-September 1871 (Box 1)
    (11)
  - October-December 1871 (Box 1)
    (12)
  - January-June 1872 (Box 1)
    (13)
  - July-December 1872 (Box 1)
    (14)
  - January-June 1873 (Box 1)
    (15)
  - July-December 1873 (Box 1)
    (16)
  - January-March 1874 (Box 1)
    (17)
  - April-June 1874 (Box 1)
    (18)
  - July-December 1874 (Box 1)
    (19)
  - January-June 1875 (Box 1)
    (20)
  - July-December 1875 (Box 1)
    (21)
  - January-March 1876 (Box 1)
    (22)
  - April-June 1876 (Box 1)
    (23)
  - July-September 1876 (Box 1)
    (24)
  - October-December 1876 (Box 1)
    (25)
  - January-February 1877 (Box 1)
    (26)
  - March 1877 (Box 1)
    (27)
  - April 1877 (Box 1)
    (28)
  - May 1877 (Box 1)
    (29)
  - June 1877 (Box 1)
    (30)
  - July 1-15, 1877 (Box 1)
    (31)
  - July 16-31, 1877 (Box 1)
    (32)
  - August 1877 (Box 1)
    (33)
  - September-October 1877 (Box 1)
    (34)
  - November-December 1877 (Box 1)
    (35)
  - January-March 1878 (Box 1)
    (36)
  - April 1878 (Box 1)
    (37)
  - May 1878 (Box 1)
    (38)
  - June 1878 (Box 1)
    (39)
  - July-August 1878 (Box 1)
    (40)
  - September-October 1878 (Box 1)
    (41)
  - November-December 1878 (Box 1)
    (42)
  - January-March 1879 (Box 1)
    (43)
  - April-June 1879 (Box 1)
    (44)
  - July-September 1879 (Box 1)
    (45)
  - October-December 1879 (Box 1)
    (46)
  - January-February 1880 (Box 2)
    (47)
  - March 1880 (Box 2)
    (48)
  - April 1880 (Box 2)
    (49)
  - May 1880 (Box 2)
    (50)
  - June 1880 (Box 2)
    (51)
  - July-August 1880 (Box 2)
    (52)
  - September 1880 (Box 2)
    (53)
  - October 1880 (Box 2)
    (54)
  - November 1880 (Box 2)
    (55)
  - December 1880 (Box 2)
    (56)
  - Jan 1-15 1881 (Box 2)
    (57)
  - January 16-31 1881 (Box 2)
    (58)
  - February 1881 (Box 2)
    (59)
  - March 1881 (Box 2)
    (60)
  - April 1881 (Box 2)
    (61)
  - May 1881 (Box 2)
    (62)
  - June 1881 (Box 2)
    (63)
  - July 1881 (Box 2)
    (64)
  - August 1881 (Box 2)
    (65)
  - September 1881 (Box 2)
    (66)
  - October-December 1881 (Box 2)
    (67)
  - January-March 1882 (Box 2)
    (68)
  - April 1882 (Box 2)
    (69)
  - May-June 1882 (Box 2)
    (70)
  - July-September 1882 (Box 2)
    (71)
  - October-December 1882 (Box 2)
    (72)
  - January-June 1883 (Box 2)
    (73)
  - July-August 1883 (Box 2)
    (74)
  - September-October 1883 (Box 2)
    (75)
  - November 1883 (Box 2)
    (76)
  - December 1-7, 1883 (Box 2)
    (77)
  - December 8-31, 1883 (Box 2)
    (78)
  - January-March 1884 (Box 2)
    (79)
  - April-June 1884 (Box 2)
    (80)
  - July-September 1884 (Box 2)
    (81)
  - October-December 1884 (Box 2)
    (82)
  - January-March 1885 (Box 2)
    (83)
  - April 1885 (Box 2)
    (84)
  - May-June 1885 (Box 2)
    (85)
  - July-September 1885 (Box 3)
    (86)
  - October-December 1885 (Box 3)
    (87)
  - January-March 1886 (Box 3)
    (88)
  - April-June 1886 (Box 3)
    (89)
  - July-December 1886 (Box 3)
    (90)
  - January-February 1887 (Box 3)
    (91)
  - March 1887 (Box 3)
    (92)
  - April 1887 (Box 3)
    (93)
  - May-June 1887 (Box 3)
    (94)
  - July-August 1887 (Box 3)
    (95)
  - September-October 1887 (Box 3)
    (96)
  - November-December 1887 (Box 3)
    (97)
  - January-March 1888 (Box 3)
    (98)
  - April 1888 (Box 3)
    (99)
  - May-June 1888 (Box 3)
    (100)
  - July-September 1888 (Box 3)
    (101)
  - October-December 1888 (Box 3)
    (102)
  - January-February 1889 (Box 3)
    (103)
  - March 1889 (Box 3)
    (104)
  - April-June 1889 (Box 3)
    (105)
  - July-September 1889 (Box 3)
    (106)
  - October-December 1889 (Box 3)
    (107)
  - January-February 1890 (Box 3)
    (108)
  - March 1890 (Box 3)
    (109)
  - April 1890 (Box 3)
    (110)
  - May 1890 (Box 3)
    (111)
  - June 1890 (Box 3)
    (112)
  - July-August 1890 (Box 3)
    (113)
  - September-October 1890 (Box 3)
    (114)
  - November 1890 (Box 3)
    (115)
  - December 1890 (Box 3)
    (116)
  - January 1-15, 1891 (Box 3)
    (117)
  - January 16-31, 1891 (Box 3)
    (118)
  - February 1891 (Box 3)
    (119)
  - March 1891 (Box 3)
    (120)
  - April 1891 (Box 4)
    (121)
  - May 1891 (Box 4)
    (122)
  - June 1891 (Box 4)
    (123)
  - July-September 1891 (Box 4)
    (124)
  - October-December 1891 (Box 4)
    (125)
  - January-March 1892 (Box 4)
    (126)
  - April-June 1892 (Box 4)
    (127)
  - July-September 1892 (Box 4)
    (128)
  - October-December 1892 (Box 4)
    (129)
  - January-February 1893 (Box 4)
    (130)
  - March 1893 (Box 4)
    (131)
  - April 1893 (Box 4)
    (132)
  - May-June 1893 (Box 4)
    (133)
  - July-September 1893 (Box 4)
    (134)
  - October 1893 (Box 4)
    (135)
  - November 1893 (Box 4)
    (136)
  - December 1893 (Box 4)
    (137)
  - January-February 1894 (Box 4)
    (138)
  - March-April 1894 (Box 4)
    (139)
  - May-June 1894 (Box 4)
    (140)
  - July-September 1894 (Box 4)
    (141)
  - October-December 1894 (Box 4)
    (142)
  - January-March 1895 (Box 4)
    (143)
  - April 1895 (Box 4)
    (144)
  - May-June 1895 (Box 4)
    (145)
  - July-September 1895 (Box 4)
    (146)
  - October 1895 (Box 4)
    (147)
  - November 1895 (Box 4)
    (148)
  - December 1895 (Box 4)
    (149)
  - January 1896 (Box 4)
    (150)
  - February 1-15, 1896 (Box 4)
    (151)
  - February 16-28, 1896 (Box 4)
    (152)
  - March 1-15, 1896 (Box 4)
    (153)
  - March 16-31, 1896 (Box 4)
    (154)
  - April 1896 (Box 4)
    (155)
  - May 1896 (Box 4)
    (156)
  - June 1-15, 1896 (Box 4)
    (157)
  - June 16-30, 1896 (Box 4)
    (158)
  - July-September 1896 (Box 5)
    (159)
  - October-December 1896 (Box 5)
    (160)
  - January 1897 (Box 5)
    (161)
  - February 1897 (Box 5)
    (162)
  - March 1897 (Box 5)
    (163)
  - April 1-15, 1897 (Box 5)
    (164)
  - April 16-30, 1897 (Box 5)
    (165)
  - May-June 1897 (Box 5)
    (166)
  - July-December 1897 (Box 5)
    (167)
  - January-June 1898 (Box 5)
    (168)
  - August 1898 (Box 5)
    (169)
  - September 1898 (Box 5)
    (170)
  - October-December 1898 (Box 5)
    (171)
  - January-February 1899 (Box 5)
    (172)
  - March-April 1899 (Box 5)
    (173)
  - May-June 1899 (Box 5)
    (174)
  - July-September 1899 (Box 5)
    (175)
  - October-December 1899 (Box 5)
    (176)
  - January-February 1900 (Box 5)
    (177)
  - March-April 1900 (Box 5)
    (178)
  - May-June 1900 (Box 5)
    (179)
  - July-September 1900 (Box 5)
    (180)
  - October-December 1900 (Box 5)
    (181)
  - January-March 1901 (Box 5)
    (182)
  - April-June 1901 (Box 5)
    (183)
  - July-September 1901 (Box 5)
    (184)
  - October-December 1901 (Box 5)
    (185)
  - January-February 1902 (Box 5)
    (186)
  - March-April 1902 (Box 5)
    (187)
  - May-June 1902 (Box 5)
    (188)
  - July-September 1902 (Box 5)
    (189)
  - October-December 1902 (Box 5)
    (190)
  - January-March 1903 (Box 5)
    (191)
  - April-June 1903 (Box 5)
    (192)
  - July-September 1903 (Box 5)
    (193)
  - October 1903 (Box 5)
    (194)
  - November 1903 (Box 5)
    (195)
  - December 1-15, 1903 (Box 5)
    (196)
  - December 16-17, 1903 (Box 5)
    (197)
  - December 18, 1903 (Box 6)
    (198)
  - December 19-20, 1903 (Box 6)
    (199)
  - December 21-23, 1903 (Box 6)
    (200)
  - December 24-31, 1903 (Box 6)
    (201)
  - January 1904 (Box 6)
    (202)
  - February 1904 (Box 6)
    (203)
  - March-April 1904 (Box 6)
    (204)
  - May 1904 (Box 6)
    (205)
  - June 1904 (Box 6)
    (206)
  - July-September 1904 (Box 6)
    (207)
  - October 1904 (Box 6)
    (208)
  - November-December 1904 (Box 6)
    (209)
  - January 1905 (Box 6)
    (210)
  - February 1905 (Box 6)
    (211)
  - March-April 1905 (Box 6)
    (212)
  - May-June 1905 (Box 6)
    (213)
  - July-September 1905 (Box 6)
    (214)
  - October 1905 (Box 6)
    (215)
  - November 1905 (Box 6)
    (216)
  - December 1905 (Box 6)
    (217)
  - January 1906 (Box 6)
    (218)
  - February 1906 (Box 6)
    (219)
  - March-April 1906 (Box 6)
    (220)
  - May-June 1906 (Box 6)
    (221)
  - July-September 1906 (Box 6)
    (222)
  - October 1906 (Box 6)
    (223)
  - November 1906 (Box 6)
    (224)
  - December 1906 (Box 6)
    (225)
  - January-February 1907 (Box 6)
    (226)
  - March-April 1907 (Box 6)
    (227)
  - May-June 1907 (Box 6)
    (228)
  - July-September 1907 (Box 6)
    (229)
  - October-December 1907 (Box 6)
    (230)
  - January 1908 (Box 6)
    (231)
  - February 1908 (Box 6)
    (232)
  - March 1908 (Box 6)
    (233)
  - April 1908 (Box 6)
    (234)
  - May 1908 (Box 6)
    (235)
  - June 1908 (Box 6)
    (236)
  - July-September 1908 (Box 6)
    (237)
  - October-December 1908 (Box 7)
    (238)
  - January 1-7, 1909 (Box 7)
    (239)
  - January 8-15, 1909 (Box 7)
    (240)
  - January 16-31, 1909 (Box 7)
    (241)
  - February 1909 (Box 7)
    (242)
  - March 1909 (Box 7)
    (243)
  - April 1909 (Box 7)
    (244)
  - May-June 1909 (Box 7)
    (245)
  - July-September 1909 (Box 7)
    (246)
  - October-December 1909 (Box 7)
    (247)
  - January-June 1910 (Box 7)
    (248)
  - July-December 1910 (Box 7)
    (249)
  - 1911 (Box 7)
    (250)
  - 1912 (Box 7)
    (251)
  - 1913 (Box 7)
    (252)
  - 1914 (Box 7)
    (253)
  - 1915 (Box 7)
    (254)
  - January-February 1916 (Box 7)
    (255)
  - Undated (Box 7)
    (256)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    (include copies of letters from Angell to A.D. White; originals in Cornell University archives)
    (257)
  - Non-Angell correspondence (include A.G. Bell) (Box 7)
    (258)
  - Regarding death of Sarah Angell, 1903 (Box 7)
    (include memorials and clippings)
    (259)
  - Regarding Rhodes Scholarships, July 1903-February 1909; 8 folders (Box 7)
    (260-267)
- Addresses and Articles, 1849-1914; 2.6 linear feet
  Angell was a frequent speaker at civic and ceremonial events, high school and college commencements, to scholarly and professional organizations, religious groups, and the students and faculty of the university. The Addresses and articles series contains texts and outlines of speeches and a number of published articles, many of which originated as speeches. The addresses and article cover a wide range of topics including, education, religion, international affairs - especially in regard to China, and civic and patriotic themes. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellanea (Box 8)
    (includes writings of Angell as a boy; also undated essay on "Race Questions")
    (285)
  - 1845-1849
    - Papers written while a student at Brown University (Box 8)
      (286)
  - 1849
    - "History of My Religious Experience," December 31 (Box 8)
      (287)
  - 1850
    - Outline of remarks delivered at dedication of School House District No. 14 (Rhode Island) February 9 (Box 8)
      (288)
  - 1853-1860
    - Examination questions for French classes, Brown University (Box 8)
      (289)
  - 1854
    - Lectures on German life and literature, May 5 (Box 8)
      (290)
    - "History and Characteristics of the French Language," May 8 (Box 8)
      (291-292)
    - "Teaching by Love in Sunday Schools," June 17; Fourth of July Address at N. Scituate Sabbath School (Box 8)
      (293)
    - Rhode Island Art Appreciation, September 4; outline of speech given in Wakefield, R. I. on Library, June, 1855 (Box 8)
      (294)
    - "A Visit to Wakulla Spring, by William the Wanderer," Chap. I, etc. (Box 8)
      (295)
  - 1855
    - Lecture on American Principles in Europe, December 22 (Box 8)
      (296)
    - "The Influence of America in the Diffusion of Republican Principles in Europe," December 22 (Box 8)
      (297)
    - Germans in America; Paper on the German language; Translation of "The Solution and Reproduction of India Rubber ..." (Box 8)
      (298)
    - "On the Life and Character of Emanuel Geibel" (Box 8)
      (299)
  - 1856
    - Address before the Society of Missionary Inquiry, Brown University, January 7. (Box 8)
      (300)
    - Review of Lewes' Life of Goethe, March 10. (Box 8)
      (301)
    - "Scenes in the Western District," published in Putnam's Magazine May. (Box 8)
      (302)
    - The French Language, May; notes for edition of Manual of French Literature; re DeVigry (?) "Cinq Mars" (Box 8)
      (303)
    - The Maiden's Lake (or Pond), June 3. (Box 8)
      (304)
  - 1857
    - Address delivered at the dedication of the New Hall of Warren Ladies' Seminary, July 21. (Box 8)
      (305)
    - "Influence of English Literature on the German," (published in the North American Review) (Box 8)
      (306)
    - "The Royal House of St. Cyr;" (published in the North American Review in 1867) (Box 8)
      (307)
  - 1858
    - "The Scientific Study of Literature," oration to the United Brothers' and Philemenian Societies (Box 8)
      (308)
  - 1858-1860
    - Relation of Education to Labor, address delivered in New England. (Box 8)
      (309)
  - 1859
    - Speech at the Mt. Vernon Festival, Railroad Hall, Providence, March 8. (Box 8)
      (310)